<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Haproxy on</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/tags/haproxy/</link><description>Recent content in Haproxy on</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2021 22:17:23 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/tags/haproxy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>DIY 5$: deploy Wordpress + free SSL with letsencrypt and haproxy</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/wordpress-haproxy-letsencrypt-free-ssl/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2021 22:17:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/wordpress-haproxy-letsencrypt-free-ssl/</guid><description>&lt;p>If you are starting your new business or want to have your own blog, hosting your website is something are looking for. But you are asking yourself: &amp;ldquo;What is a cheap and good way to host my website?&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Well, I have asked myself the same question and I got the answer. I had already an &lt;a onclick="gtag('event', 'aliexpress', {'event_category': 'click','event_label': 'orangepi'})" href="https://s.click.aliexpress.com/e/_DmzBfXl" target="_blank">Orange pi&lt;/a>, so I have decided to use it and deploy my website on it. It has been working since 5 months without any trouble or disfunction.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>HAProxy LetsEncrypt Docker Tutorial: Create and Renew HTTPs Certificates for free</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/haproxy-letsencrypt-docker-certbot-certificates/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 17:57:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/haproxy-letsencrypt-docker-certbot-certificates/</guid><description>&lt;p>If you are looking to secure your website/API for free and found yourself on this page, that means you are on the good path :)
Securing pages are required for security reasons, but also improve your ranking on search engines and can impact your social visibility.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This tutorial will show how to secure a golang API using HAProxy and letsencrypt.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="whats-letsencrypt">What&amp;rsquo;s LetsEncrypt&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://letsencrypt.org">LetsEncrypt&lt;/a> is a free certificate authority launched on 2016. It automates the delivery of certificates used to secure the traffic. The certificate is valid for 90 days.
The protocol ACME (Automated Certificate Management Environment) is used by LetsEncrypt to proof that you are the domain owner, to generate the certificate and to renew it.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>