<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>air quality on</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/tags/air-quality/</link><description>Recent content in air quality on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/tags/air-quality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Control and Automate Air Purifier with ESP32 and Home Assistant Air Quality Index</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/automate-air-purifier-esp32-home-assistant-aqi/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/automate-air-purifier-esp32-home-assistant-aqi/</guid><description>I’ve always been a bit obsessive about air quality. Living in a city, you notice the difference a good air purifier makes, but I got tired of manually turning it on every time the pollution levels spiked. It felt, well, decidedly un-smart. So I set out to fix that by creating a system where my air purifier automatically kicks in when the Home Assistant Air Quality Index (AQI) reaches a certain threshold.</description></item><item><title>HomeAssistant Air Quality Monitoring: Why PMS5003 with ESP32 is the Best Combo for 2025</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/homeassistant-air-quality-pms5003-esp32-2025/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/homeassistant-air-quality-pms5003-esp32-2025/</guid><description>HomeAssistant Air Quality Monitoring: Why PMS5003 with ESP32 is the Best Combo for 2025 Ever wondered why your allergies act up indoors or why that mysterious &amp;ldquo;musty smell&amp;rdquo; lingers? I did—until I built my own air quality monitor using a PMS5003 sensor and ESP32. In 2025, with wildfires, pollen, and urban pollution on the rise, monitoring air quality isn’t just a luxury—it’s a necessity. Here’s why this combo is unbeatable and how to set it up with HomeAssistant.</description></item></channel></rss>