<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>esp32 on</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/tags/esp32/</link><description>Recent content in esp32 on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/tags/esp32/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Control Lights Based on Room Occupancy Using PIR and ESP32</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/control-lights-room-occupancy-pir-esp32/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/control-lights-room-occupancy-pir-esp32/</guid><description>Control Lights Based on Room Occupancy Using PIR and ESP32 Ever walked into a room, arms full of groceries, only to fumble for the light switch? Or worse—left the lights on all day in an empty room? With a PIR motion sensor and an ESP32, you can automate your lights to turn on when someone enters and off when the room is vacant. It’s a simple yet powerful way to save energy and add convenience to your smart home.</description></item><item><title>ESP32 + OLED Display: Display Weather from Home Assistant</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-oled-display-weather-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-oled-display-weather-home-assistant/</guid><description>ESP32 + OLED Display: Display Weather from Home Assistant Ever wanted a sleek, always-on display showing the current weather right from your Home Assistant dashboard? I did—and after some tinkering, I built one using an ESP32 and a tiny OLED screen. In this guide, I’ll walk you through the process, sharing pitfalls I encountered (like why my first attempt showed gibberish instead of temperatures) and how to avoid them.
Why This Project?</description></item><item><title>Create an ESP32-Powered Smart Mailbox Notification System with Home Assistant</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-smart-mailbox-notification-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-smart-mailbox-notification-home-assistant/</guid><description>Create an ESP32-Powered Smart Mailbox Notification System Ever missed an important piece of mail because you forgot to check your mailbox? I certainly have—more times than I’d like to admit. That’s why I built a smart mailbox notification system using an ESP32 and a simple tilt sensor. Now, I get instant alerts in Home Assistant whenever the mailbox door opens. No more guessing!
In this guide, I’ll walk you through the entire process—from wiring the hardware to configuring ESPHome and setting up automations in Home Assistant.</description></item><item><title>Build a Smart Thermostat with ESP32, Home Assistant, and Relays</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-smart-thermostat-home-assistant-relay-sensors/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-smart-thermostat-home-assistant-relay-sensors/</guid><description>Build a Smart Thermostat with ESP32 and Home Assistant Using Relay and Sensors Ever wanted to ditch your clunky old thermostat for a DIY smart version that integrates seamlessly with Home Assistant? I did—and after a few weekends of tinkering (and a couple of fried relays), I built a reliable ESP32-based smart thermostat. Here’s how you can too.
Why Build a DIY Smart Thermostat? Commercial smart thermostats are great, but they often come with limitations: proprietary ecosystems, cloud dependencies, or lack of customization.</description></item><item><title>Voice-Controlling Your Home with ESP32 and Home Assistant via Google Assistant</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/voice-control-esp32-home-assistant-google-assistant/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/voice-control-esp32-home-assistant-google-assistant/</guid><description>Voice-Controlling Your Home with ESP32 and Home Assistant via Google Assistant Ever wished you could turn off the lights without lifting a finger—or even getting out of bed? I certainly have, especially on those lazy Sunday mornings. That’s why I set out to integrate my ESP32-based smart devices with Home Assistant and Google Assistant, enabling voice control for my entire home. In this guide, I’ll walk you through the process step by step, sharing the pitfalls I encountered (and how to avoid them) along the way.</description></item><item><title>HomeAssistant Air Quality Monitoring: Why PMS5003 with ESP32 is the Best Combo for 2025</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/homeassistant-air-quality-pms5003-esp32-2025/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/homeassistant-air-quality-pms5003-esp32-2025/</guid><description>HomeAssistant Air Quality Monitoring: Why PMS5003 with ESP32 is the Best Combo for 2025 Ever wondered why your allergies act up indoors or why that mysterious &amp;ldquo;musty smell&amp;rdquo; lingers? I did—until I built my own air quality monitor using a PMS5003 sensor and ESP32. In 2025, with wildfires, pollen, and urban pollution on the rise, monitoring air quality isn’t just a luxury—it’s a necessity. Here’s why this combo is unbeatable and how to set it up with HomeAssistant.</description></item><item><title>DIY Smart Door Sensor with ESP32 and Home Assistant: A Step-by-Step Guide</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/diy-smart-door-sensor-esp32-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/diy-smart-door-sensor-esp32-home-assistant/</guid><description>DIY Smart Door Sensor with ESP32 and Home Assistant Ever walked out the door and wondered, Did I close it? I’ve been there too—until I built a DIY smart door sensor using an ESP32 and Home Assistant. Now, my phone buzzes if the door’s left ajar, and I’ve even set up automations to turn off the AC when the door’s open for too long (goodbye, wasted energy!). Here’s how you can build your own.</description></item><item><title>Control an IR Remote AC Using ESP32 and Home Assistant</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/control-ir-ac-esp32-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/control-ir-ac-esp32-home-assistant/</guid><description>Control an IR Remote AC Using ESP32 and Home Assistant Ever wished your dumb air conditioner could join your smart home party? I did—especially during a heatwave when I realized I’d left the AC on full blast while away. Enter the ESP32, a $5 microcontroller that (with some tinkering) can emulate your AC’s IR remote and integrate it into Home Assistant. Here’s how I did it.
What You’ll Need Hardware:
ESP32-DevKit board: Buy it here
IR receiver/sender module VS1838B &amp;#43; IR LED: Buy it here
Breadboard and jumper wires USB cable for power/flashing Software: Home Assistant (installed and running) ESPHome (via Home Assistant Add-on) Pro Tip: Test your IR LED before wiring—some have narrow angles.</description></item><item><title>Automate Your Garden Watering with ESP32 and Home Assistant</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/automate-your-garden-watering-esp32-home-assitantant/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/automate-your-garden-watering-esp32-home-assitantant/</guid><description>Automate Your Garden Watering with ESP32 and Home Assistant Ever forgotten to water your plants only to find them looking like they’ve been on a desert trek? I have—more times than I’d like to admit. That’s why I built a smart garden watering system using an ESP32, soil moisture sensors, and Home Assistant. Now, my plants get watered automatically, and I get to pretend I’ve got a green thumb. Here’s how you can do it too.</description></item><item><title>Esp32 + 1$ DHT22 temperature sensor</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-dht22-temperature-humidity-sensor/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 08:14:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-dht22-temperature-humidity-sensor/</guid><description>ESPHome is a powerful framework for building IoT devices using ESP8266, ESP32, and other microcontrollers. It allows you to easily configure and control your devices from a web interface. In this tutorial, we will learn how to connect the DHT22 sensor to the ESP32 board using ESPHome. Let&amp;rsquo;s get started.
Step 1: Install ESPHome Before we begin, make sure you have installed ESPHome on your computer. Follow the instructions on the ESPHome website to install ESPHome.</description></item><item><title>Cheap 15$ Air quality monitor: ESP32, Bluetooth &amp; Home assistant</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-airquality-box-wp6003-homeassistant/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2022 08:57:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-airquality-box-wp6003-homeassistant/</guid><description>If you are a DIY lover, the first sensors you look at are : temperature sensor and airquality sensor. #Metoo.
I have started with the temperature sensor in this article and found that amazing. I decided to go try the airquality monitoring.
I wanted something cheap, and ideally with bluetooth to connect it easily to my ESP32 and Home assistant, I found that Airbox WP6003 can do the job.
Requirements:
ESP32-DevKit board: Buy it here
Airbox WP6003 Bluetooth: Buy it here
Collecting information BLE devices normally has characteristics that can be access using an ID.</description></item><item><title>ESP32 AM312 motion sensor automation</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-am312-pir-motion-sensor/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2022 21:57:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-am312-pir-motion-sensor/</guid><description>DIY 5 minutes : Connect esp32 to the motion sensor am312 and create an automation.
In the last article, we&amp;rsquo;ve seen how to turn on/off the smart light depending on the presence of your smartwatch. In this article, we will see how to turn on/off the light using the PIR motion sensor AM312.
Requirements Before starting the tutorial, you should have these materials.
Aliexpress:
ESP32-DevKit board: Buy it here
AM312 Motion sensor: Buy it here
Tuya wifi bulb: Buy it here
Wiring the components AM312 has 3 pins: 5v, GND and DATA.</description></item><item><title>How to turn off the light automatically when you go out using esp32</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/how-to-turn-off-light-automatically/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Jan 2021 20:57:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/how-to-turn-off-light-automatically/</guid><description>Everytime you go out and you forget to turn off the light !
Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, you are not alone in this situation. We are all LAZY. In this article, we will make it simple and easy to make some economy on your electric bill, but we will also contribute to save the planet.
Requirements Before starting the tutorial, you should have these materials.
ESP32-DevKit board: Buy it here
Tuya wifi bulb: Buy it here
Xiaomi MiBand: Buy it here
Finding the Mi band MAC adress if you know already your band bluetooth MAC adress, you can skip this part.</description></item><item><title>ESP32 cam tutorial: Setup a 5$ live streaming camera for your house with esphome</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-cam-tutorial/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 20:57:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-cam-tutorial/</guid><description>Yes you can monitor your house with live streaming for only 5$.
How? In this article, I will show you my test with esp32 camera. In addition, you will see how to configure it using esphome. Finally, I will show you how to connect esp32 cam to home assistant.
Requirements Before starting the tutorial, you should have these materials. Aliexpress:
ESP32-Cam: Buy it here
Jump wires
FDTI: Buy it here
If you find any problem during this tutorial: Please leave a commment and I will reply very soon!</description></item><item><title>How to connect ESP32 to home assistant in 5 minutes</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/how-to-connect-esp32-esphome-to-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2020 20:57:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/how-to-connect-esp32-esphome-to-home-assistant/</guid><description>How to connect ESP32 configured with ESPhome to home assistant.
In the last article, we&amp;rsquo;ve seen how to configure an ESP32 chip with ESPhome and how to connect it to Xiomi Mijia thermometer. Now, we will discover how to have a good graphical interface to monitor the temperature of the room.
What is home assistant? Home assistant is an open source software that let you monitor IoT devices in your home.</description></item><item><title>Esphome Tutorial: for 4$ monitor your home temperature with esp32 and xiaomi mijia</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/how-to-monitor-your-home-temperature-with-esp32-and-xiaomi-mijia-using-esphome/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2020 20:57:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/how-to-monitor-your-home-temperature-with-esp32-and-xiaomi-mijia-using-esphome/</guid><description>We live in a world where everything is connected. One day, I wanted to know the temperature of my house when I&amp;rsquo;m outside to check if the heating regulator is working or not. Already having a bluetooth Xiaomi Mijia lywsd03mmc thermometer, I was looking for something cheap and tiny to do connect to the thermometer and do the job.
I did some research and found a chip called ESP32. This chip has integrated bluetooth and WIFI.</description></item></channel></rss>