<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>home automation on</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/tags/home-automation/</link><description>Recent content in home automation on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/tags/home-automation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>DIY ESP32-Based Motion Sensor for Home Assistant Security Automations</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-pir-motion-sensor-home-assistant-automation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-pir-motion-sensor-home-assistant-automation/</guid><description>DIY ESP32-Based Motion Sensor for Home Assistant Security Automations Ever walked into a dark room and wished the lights would just know to turn on? Or wanted a simple way to alert you when someone’s lurking near your front door? That’s where a DIY ESP32-based PIR motion sensor comes in. I recently built one to integrate with Home Assistant, and it’s been a game-changer for my home security automations. Here’s how you can do it too—no PhD in electrical engineering required.</description></item><item><title>Control Lights Based on Room Occupancy Using PIR and ESP32</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/control-lights-room-occupancy-pir-esp32/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/control-lights-room-occupancy-pir-esp32/</guid><description>Control Lights Based on Room Occupancy Using PIR and ESP32 Ever walked into a room, arms full of groceries, only to fumble for the light switch? Or worse—left the lights on all day in an empty room? With a PIR motion sensor and an ESP32, you can automate your lights to turn on when someone enters and off when the room is vacant. It’s a simple yet powerful way to save energy and add convenience to your smart home.</description></item><item><title>Automate Your Curtains with a Smart Tuya Roller Chain Motor: A Step-by-Step Guide</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/automate-curtains-tuya-smart-roller-chain-motor-guide/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/automate-curtains-tuya-smart-roller-chain-motor-guide/</guid><description>Automate Your Curtains with a Smart Tuya Curtain Roller Chain Motor Ever wished your curtains could open and close on their own? Maybe you’re tired of fumbling with cords in the morning or want to impress your friends with a &amp;ldquo;Hey Google, open the curtains&amp;rdquo; moment. Whatever your reason, automating your curtains with a Tuya Smart Curtain Roller Chain Motor is easier than you think. Here’s how I did it—and how you can too.</description></item><item><title>Track Your Electricity Consumption with Shelly Pro 2PM: Advantages and Home Assistant Integration</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/track-electricity-consumption-shelly-pro-2pm-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/track-electricity-consumption-shelly-pro-2pm-home-assistant/</guid><description>Track Your Electricity Consumption with Shelly Pro 2PM: Advantages and Home Assistant Integration Ever stared at your electricity bill and wondered, &amp;ldquo;How did I use that much power?&amp;quot; I certainly have. That’s why I decided to take control by monitoring my home’s energy consumption in real-time using the Shelly Pro 2PM—a versatile, Wi-Fi-enabled energy monitoring device. In this guide, I’ll walk you through setting it up, integrating it with Home Assistant, and turning raw data into actionable insights.</description></item><item><title>DIY Smart Door Sensor with ESP32 and Home Assistant: A Step-by-Step Guide</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/diy-smart-door-sensor-esp32-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/diy-smart-door-sensor-esp32-home-assistant/</guid><description>DIY Smart Door Sensor with ESP32 and Home Assistant Ever walked out the door and wondered, Did I close it? I’ve been there too—until I built a DIY smart door sensor using an ESP32 and Home Assistant. Now, my phone buzzes if the door’s left ajar, and I’ve even set up automations to turn off the AC when the door’s open for too long (goodbye, wasted energy!). Here’s how you can build your own.</description></item><item><title>Control an IR Remote AC Using ESP32 and Home Assistant</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/control-ir-ac-esp32-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/control-ir-ac-esp32-home-assistant/</guid><description>Control an IR Remote AC Using ESP32 and Home Assistant Ever wished your dumb air conditioner could join your smart home party? I did—especially during a heatwave when I realized I’d left the AC on full blast while away. Enter the ESP32, a $5 microcontroller that (with some tinkering) can emulate your AC’s IR remote and integrate it into Home Assistant. Here’s how I did it.
What You’ll Need Hardware:
ESP32-DevKit board: Buy it here
IR receiver/sender module VS1838B &amp;#43; IR LED: Buy it here
Breadboard and jumper wires USB cable for power/flashing Software: Home Assistant (installed and running) ESPHome (via Home Assistant Add-on) Pro Tip: Test your IR LED before wiring—some have narrow angles.</description></item><item><title>Automate Your Garden Watering with ESP32 and Home Assistant</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/automate-your-garden-watering-esp32-home-assitantant/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/automate-your-garden-watering-esp32-home-assitantant/</guid><description>Automate Your Garden Watering with ESP32 and Home Assistant Ever forgotten to water your plants only to find them looking like they’ve been on a desert trek? I have—more times than I’d like to admit. That’s why I built a smart garden watering system using an ESP32, soil moisture sensors, and Home Assistant. Now, my plants get watered automatically, and I get to pretend I’ve got a green thumb. Here’s how you can do it too.</description></item></channel></rss>