<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>time-series on</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/tags/time-series/</link><description>Recent content in time-series on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/tags/time-series/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to Set Up Prometheus Remote Write to Push Metrics to VictoriaMetrics</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/prometheus-remote-write-victoriametrics-setup/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/prometheus-remote-write-victoriametrics-setup/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been running my own monitoring stack for years, and if there&amp;rsquo;s one thing I&amp;rsquo;ve learned, it&amp;rsquo;s that Prometheus alone can feel like trying to store all your holiday decorations in a single shoebox. It works fine at first, but soon you&amp;rsquo;re dealing with capacity issues and wondering where that one crucial metric from three months ago disappeared to.
That&amp;rsquo;s why I recently set up Prometheus remote write to push metrics to VictoriaMetrics for centralized, long-retention storage.</description></item><item><title>Visualizing Time Series Data Using Grafana’s Transform and Threshold Tools</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/visualizing-time-series-data-grafana-transform-threshold-tools/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/visualizing-time-series-data-grafana-transform-threshold-tools/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been staring at Grafana dashboards for years now—first while monitoring complex cloud infrastructure, and more recently to keep tabs on my increasingly smart (and sometimes overly opinionated) home. There&amp;rsquo;s a particular frustration that comes with a dashboard that shows data but doesn&amp;rsquo;t tell a story. You know the one: a tangled mess of lines on a graph, all in the same color, leaving you squinting and asking, &amp;ldquo;Okay, but is this good or bad?</description></item></channel></rss>