<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title/><link>https://omarghader.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2014 20:53:07 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Docker Compose Nginx Tutorial</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/docker-compose-nginx-tutorial/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/docker-compose-nginx-tutorial/</guid><description>1. What is nginx? Nginx is a reverse proxy, HTTP cache and load balancer. It aims to enhance performance by using less memory. Nginx is event-driven. That measns it uses one thread to receive requests, then it dispatch it to one or multiple threads asynchronously.
In this post, you will learn how to deploy a load balancer using nginx in docker.
2. Requirements Docker Docker compose 3. How it works Supposing you have 2 servers server1 and server2 that expose a web service.</description></item><item><title>How to center a element inside div with css</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/how-to-center-a-element-inside-div-with-css/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/how-to-center-a-element-inside-div-with-css/</guid><description>Centering elements inside div is a common problem in web development. In this post I will explain a very easy solution for this that works always.
Before centering Let&amp;rsquo;s say we have those 2 containers.
&amp;lt;div class=&amp;#34;container&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;div class=&amp;#34;center-element&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt; &amp;lt;style&amp;gt; .container { width: 300px; height: 300px; background: red; } .center-element{ width: 200px; height: 200px; background: yellow; } &amp;lt;/style&amp;gt; Centering the element The easiest way is to use the flex display that handles the centering in very good way.</description></item><item><title>Monitor your applications easily with Grafana and Prometheus</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/monitor-your-applications-easily-with-grafana-and-prometheus/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/monitor-your-applications-easily-with-grafana-and-prometheus/</guid><description>1. What is Prometheus &amp;amp; Grafana? Prometheus is a monitoring system which collects metrics from applications easily. Grafana is a user-friendly visualization project which transforms the metrics collected before into amazing charts. In this article, you will learn how to connect prometheus to grafana using a docker compose file.
2. Requirements Install docker Install docker compose Golang &amp;gt;= 1.08 3. Create your application If you want to get metrics from your application, the first step is to add prometheus to your application code.</description></item><item><title>Configuring Node js on Jenkins using docker</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/jenkins-nodejs-configuration/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/jenkins-nodejs-configuration/</guid><description>Jenkins is a devops tool for continuous intergration.
Install jenkins Requirements for this tutorial :
Docker Docker compose We will user docker compose to configure jenkins docker container:
version: &amp;#39;3.5&amp;#39; services: jenkins: image: &amp;#39;jenkins/jenkins:lts&amp;#39; container_name: &amp;#39;jenkins&amp;#39; restart: always ports: - &amp;#39;8080:8080&amp;#39; - &amp;#39;50000:50000&amp;#39; volumes: - jenkins-data:/etc/gitlab - /var/run/docker.sock:/var/run/docker.sock volumes: jenkins-data: name: jenkins-data Then, run the command :
$ docker-compose up -d Run Jenkins Once you had run the docker compose file, test that your jenkins is running by opening this url on your browser http://localhost:8080</description></item><item><title>Docker Compose Tutorial</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/docker-compose-tutorial/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/docker-compose-tutorial/</guid><description>If you are tired of configuring your docker containers every time you want to run it, docker compose is the solution. Docker compose is a tool that will read a configuration file, and will translate it to docker command easily.
If you like this article, leave a comment and share it with your friends :)
Install Docker compose $ sudo curl -L https://github.com/docker/compose/releases/download/1.18.0/docker-compose-`uname -s`-`uname -m` -o /usr/local/bin/docker-compose $ sudo chmod +x /usr/local/bin/docker-compose # Test the installation $ docker-compose --version docker-compose version 1.</description></item><item><title>Executing R From Java Using JRI Library</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/executing-r-from-java-using-jri-library/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/executing-r-from-java-using-jri-library/</guid><description>R is a very powerful language designed for mathematics and statistics. It became one of the best data analysis tools due to its performance and its syntax simplicity. R can import datasets or generate a csv file with 1 line of code.
So, It will be very important to use R with one of the most known programming languages : JAVA. Using JRI library, i will show you how to assign variables, run R scripts&amp;hellip;.</description></item><item><title>Docker Tutorial : PhpMyAdmin and MySQL Server</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/docker-tutorial-phpmyadmin-and-mysql-server/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/docker-tutorial-phpmyadmin-and-mysql-server/</guid><description>If you are new to Docker or you are wondering why docker is very popular today, I recommend you to read my previous posts Introduction to Docker.
Pull Containers from Docker registry Searching for containers Docker have a public registry where you could find images of dockerized application that are ready to use. All information and indications for using container are specified too.
In this post, I will show you how to connect PhpMyAdmin container to MySQL server container.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Docker</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/introduction-to-docker/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/introduction-to-docker/</guid><description>Docker is a new open-source project that makes deployment of applications easier. The idea of this technology is very simple : &amp;ldquo;the application runs inside a software container. This container is acting like a mini Operating System&amp;rdquo;. Basics are very similar to Virtual machine : An OS is running independently of host&amp;rsquo;s OS. Networking is working using bridges&amp;hellip; Docker is using 2 terms : image and container:
An image is a packaged application that is not running.</description></item><item><title>My First Post</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/my-first-post/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/my-first-post/</guid><description>Hi, This is my first post. I&amp;rsquo;m computer and communication engineering student at INSA Toulouse. I&amp;rsquo;m interested in programming in : Java , C , Go lang and Javascript&amp;hellip; Also, I&amp;rsquo;m interested in Android development , Web apps, and Security DevOps, and Linux Administration. I would like to use this blog to share information about computer science.
Android development My Future posts will be related to these subjects. My tutorials will be focused on simplifying and coding android applications efficiently.</description></item><item><title>About me</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2014 20:53:07 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/about/</guid><description>Master of Software and Network Engineering at INSA de Toulouse. I specialize in Internet Of Things (IoT). Software FullStack Engineer, DevOps and Mobile Developer. I am very passionated by new technologies, curious and always motivated.
Achievements : Android application : 45000 downloads (in 6 months) Backend : Languages: Go lang, Java ,C, python, NodeJs MessageQueue : RabbitMq Relational Database : MongoDB, MySql, PostgreSql Graph Database : Neo4j DevOps : provisioning : Ansible, Salt Stack, Puppet virtualization : Vagrant , Docker Scalability : HaProxy , confd, Creation of Micro-Services Discovery : etcd Orchestration : Kubernetes Frontend : HTML5 ,JS, CSS Mobile : Ionic, Angularjs, ReactJs, Native (java) Framework : Bootstrap, Material Design UI / UX Data Science and Big Data : Machine Learning : R, H2o Data&amp;rsquo;s Features Extraction Data cleaning Behavior Detection ( Prediction )</description></item></channel></rss>