<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tutorial on</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/tags/tutorial/</link><description>Recent content in tutorial on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 08:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/tags/tutorial/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Detect Outliers in Your Metrics: A Practical Guide to Grafana Machine Learning</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/grafana-machine-learning-anomaly-detection-tutorial/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/grafana-machine-learning-anomaly-detection-tutorial/</guid><description>I’ve always been the kind of person who stares at a Grafana dashboard, watching a squiggly line, and wondering, “Is that dip normal? Should I be worried?” For years, my answer was to set up a basic threshold alert. If CPU usage goes above 90%, page someone. But what about the weird, subtle stuff? The slow creep of memory leakage or the sudden, inexplicable drop in request rate that doesn&amp;rsquo;t cross any static line but just feels… off?</description></item><item><title>Log Aggregation Using Grafana Loki: A Beginner’s Guide</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/grafana-loki-log-aggregation-beginners-guide/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/grafana-loki-log-aggregation-beginners-guide/</guid><description>Log Aggregation Using Grafana Loki: A Beginner’s Guide Ever stared at a mountain of logs, desperately searching for that one error that crashed your service? I’ve been there—more times than I’d like to admit. That’s why I fell in love with Grafana Loki, a lightweight log aggregation system that pairs perfectly with Grafana for seamless troubleshooting.
In this guide, I’ll walk you through setting up Loki to collect logs and correlate them with metrics in Grafana.</description></item><item><title>Docker Compose Tutorial</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/docker-compose-tutorial/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/docker-compose-tutorial/</guid><description>If you are tired of configuring your docker containers every time you want to run it, docker compose is the solution. Docker compose is a tool that will read a configuration file, and will translate it to docker command easily.
If you like this article, leave a comment and share it with your friends :)
Requirement For this tutorial, you need a linux machine. I am using an Orangepi server because it is very performant and affordable.</description></item></channel></rss>