<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>prometheus on</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/tags/prometheus/</link><description>Recent content in prometheus on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2023 08:14:23 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/tags/prometheus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to send duplicate RemoteWrite metrics</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/prometheus-duplicate-remotewrite/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2023 08:14:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/prometheus-duplicate-remotewrite/</guid><description>When working with metrics, you may want to send the metrics you&amp;rsquo;ve collected to 2 different prometheus instances for backup. Despite that a feature in Prometheus allows you send the metrics received to another prometheus, it&amp;rsquo;s not recommended to do that when working with high amounts of metrics.
Indeed, Prometheus consumes a lot of resources to do the remotewrite and this may reduce its capability to perform well. But other solution exists : lightweight, simple and works perfectly.</description></item><item><title>Grafana 9 Alert : How to customize alert message</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/grafana-alerting-custom-message/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2022 11:09:41 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/grafana-alerting-custom-message/</guid><description>Grafana added the alert feature recently and it&amp;rsquo;s now released with the Grafana 9. That&amp;rsquo;s a great feature for the people who don&amp;rsquo;t want to set a proper alermanager and to configure it. I&amp;rsquo;ve took the time to explore the alert and play with it. Let&amp;rsquo;s see how it works!
Deploy grafana and prometheus With the docker-compose file below run the grafana and prometheus docker-compose up -d.
# docker-compose.yml file version: &amp;#34;3.</description></item><item><title>Monitor your applications easily with Grafana and Prometheus</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/monitor-your-applications-easily-with-grafana-and-prometheus/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/monitor-your-applications-easily-with-grafana-and-prometheus/</guid><description>1. What is Prometheus &amp;amp; Grafana? Prometheus is a monitoring system which collects metrics from applications easily. Grafana is a user-friendly visualization project which transforms the metrics collected before into amazing charts. In this article, you will learn how to connect prometheus to grafana using a docker compose file.
2. Requirements Install docker Install docker compose Golang &amp;gt;= 1.08 3. Create your application If you want to get metrics from your application, the first step is to add prometheus to your application code.</description></item></channel></rss>