<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>MQTT on</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/tags/mqtt/</link><description>Recent content in MQTT on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 08:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/tags/mqtt/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Build a Room Occupancy Tracker with ESP32 and Ultrasonic Sensors</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-ultrasonic-room-occupancy-tracker/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-ultrasonic-room-occupancy-tracker/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been tinkering with smart home automation for years, always looking for clever ways to make my home more responsive. Commercial room occupancy sensors work fine, but they&amp;rsquo;re expensive and often limited in functionality. After one too many instances of my smart lights turning off while I was still reading in my favorite armchair, I decided to build my own room occupancy tracker using an ESP32 and ultrasonic sensors.
The beauty of this approach?</description></item><item><title>Build a Smart Light Dimmer with ESP32 and a Rotary Encoder in Home Assistant</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-rotary-encoder-smart-light-dimmer-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-rotary-encoder-smart-light-dimmer-home-assistant/</guid><description>I’ve always loved the tactile feel of a good knob. While voice commands and smartphone apps are convenient, there’s something deeply satisfying about physically turning a dial to dim the lights. I wanted to bridge that gap between the digital smarts of Home Assistant and the physical world. So, I set out to build a custom smart light dimmer with ESP32 and a rotary encoder.
The goal was simple: a knob that not only controls my smart lights locally but also stays perfectly in sync with their state in Home Assistant.</description></item></channel></rss>