<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>monitoring on</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/tags/monitoring/</link><description>Recent content in monitoring on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 08:14:23 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/tags/monitoring/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Vmalert: Revamp your Prometheus alert with microservices</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/vmalert-setup/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 08:14:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/vmalert-setup/</guid><description>Setup a vmalert.
While collecting metrics is important for monitoring, the real end goal is not visualizing the data. The most critical goal of metrics is to create alerts in case of bad behaviors or incidents. In the Prometheus world, prometheus itself generates alerts based on the metrics collected.
Let&amp;rsquo;s discover another product of VictoriaMetrics called Vmalert. To be honest, Vmalert is not a revolutionary product, exactly like Vmagent, but its strength is the ability to do 1 role: handling alerts with the minimum resources.</description></item><item><title>How to send duplicate RemoteWrite metrics</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/prometheus-duplicate-remotewrite/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2023 08:14:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/prometheus-duplicate-remotewrite/</guid><description>When working with metrics, you may want to send the metrics you&amp;rsquo;ve collected to 2 different prometheus instances for backup. Despite that a feature in Prometheus allows you send the metrics received to another prometheus, it&amp;rsquo;s not recommended to do that when working with high amounts of metrics.
Indeed, Prometheus consumes a lot of resources to do the remotewrite and this may reduce its capability to perform well. But other solution exists : lightweight, simple and works perfectly.</description></item></channel></rss>