<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>esp32 home asistant on</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/tags/esp32-home-asistant/</link><description>Recent content in esp32 home asistant on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Jan 2021 20:57:23 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/tags/esp32-home-asistant/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to turn off the light automatically when you go out using esp32</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/how-to-turn-off-light-automatically/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Jan 2021 20:57:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/how-to-turn-off-light-automatically/</guid><description>Everytime you go out and you forget to turn off the light !
Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, you are not alone in this situation. We are all LAZY. In this article, we will make it simple and easy to make some economy on your electric bill, but we will also contribute to save the planet.
Requirements Before starting the tutorial, you should have these materials. Aliexpress:
ESP32-DevKitC board : Buy here from aliexpress Tuya wifi bulb : Buy here from aliexpress Xiaomi mi band 5 : Buy here from aliexpress Amazon:</description></item><item><title>How to connect ESP32 to home assistant in 5 minutes</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/how-to-connect-esp32-esphome-to-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2020 20:57:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/how-to-connect-esp32-esphome-to-home-assistant/</guid><description>How to connect ESP32 configured with ESPhome to home assistant.
In the last article, we&amp;rsquo;ve seen how to configure an ESP32 chip with ESPhome and how to connect it to Xiomi Mijia thermometer. Now, we will discover how to have a good graphical interface to monitor the temperature of the room.
What is home assistant? Home assistant is an open source software that let you monitor IoT devices in your home.</description></item><item><title>ESP32 AM312 motion sensor automation</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-am312-pir-motion-sensor/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 21:57:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-am312-pir-motion-sensor/</guid><description>DIY 5 minutes : Connect esp32 to the motion sensor am312 and create an automation.
In the last article, we&amp;rsquo;ve seen how to turn on/off the smart light depending on the presence of your smartwatch. In this article, we will see how to turn on/off the light using the PIR motion sensor AM312.
Requirements Before starting the tutorial, you should have these materials. Aliexpress:
ESP32-DevKitC board : Buy here from aliexpress AM312 Motion sensor : Buy here from aliexpress Tuya wifi bulb : Buy here from aliexpress Amazon:</description></item></channel></rss>