<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>DIY Smart Home on</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/tags/diy-smart-home/</link><description>Recent content in DIY Smart Home on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/tags/diy-smart-home/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Turn ESP32 Into a BLE Beacon Scanner for Presence Detection in Home Assistant</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-ble-beacon-scanner-presence-detection-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-ble-beacon-scanner-presence-detection-home-assistant/</guid><description>Before we begin: This guide assumes you have Home Assistant already set up and are comfortable with basic ESPHome configurations. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried nearly every presence detection method in my smart home journey - from WiFi-based tracking that drained my phone battery to GPS solutions that were anything but reliable indoors. That&amp;rsquo;s when I discovered the magic of BLE beacon scanning with ESP32 for room-level presence detection. It&amp;rsquo;s been a game-changer for my home automations, and today I&amp;rsquo;ll show you exactly how to set it up.</description></item><item><title>DIY ESP32-Based Motion Sensor for Home Assistant Security Automations</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-pir-motion-sensor-home-assistant-automation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-pir-motion-sensor-home-assistant-automation/</guid><description>DIY ESP32-Based Motion Sensor for Home Assistant Security Automations Ever walked into a dark room and wished the lights would just know to turn on? Or wanted a simple way to alert you when someone’s lurking near your front door? That’s where a DIY ESP32-based PIR motion sensor comes in. I recently built one to integrate with Home Assistant, and it’s been a game-changer for my home security automations. Here’s how you can do it too—no PhD in electrical engineering required.</description></item></channel></rss>