<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>DIY on</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/tags/diy/</link><description>Recent content in DIY on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 08:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/tags/diy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Build a Room Occupancy Tracker with ESP32 and Ultrasonic Sensors</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-ultrasonic-room-occupancy-tracker/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-ultrasonic-room-occupancy-tracker/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been tinkering with smart home automation for years, always looking for clever ways to make my home more responsive. Commercial room occupancy sensors work fine, but they&amp;rsquo;re expensive and often limited in functionality. After one too many instances of my smart lights turning off while I was still reading in my favorite armchair, I decided to build my own room occupancy tracker using an ESP32 and ultrasonic sensors.
The beauty of this approach?</description></item><item><title>Control a Smart Fan with ESP32 and Home Assistant Using Temperature Triggers</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/control-smart-fan-esp32-home-assistant-temperature-triggers/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/control-smart-fan-esp32-home-assistant-temperature-triggers/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve always been fascinated with making my home smarter, especially when it comes to energy efficiency and comfort. There&amp;rsquo;s something deeply satisfying about having your home respond to environmental conditions without lifting a finger. In this tutorial, I&amp;rsquo;ll show you how I built a system that automatically controls a fan based on room temperature using an ESP32 and Home Assistant.
Why I Built This System Living in a climate with hot summers, I found myself constantly adjusting fans throughout the day.</description></item><item><title>Automating Window Blinds with ESP32 Servo Motor and Home Assistant</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/automate-window-blinds-esp32-servo-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/automate-window-blinds-esp32-servo-home-assistant/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve always been fascinated with the idea of waking up to natural sunlight instead of a blaring alarm clock. But as someone who also values sleeping in on weekends, I needed a solution that could give me the best of both worlds. That&amp;rsquo;s when I decided to automate my window blinds with an ESP32 and servo motors, integrating everything seamlessly with Home Assistant.
After a few prototypes (and one slightly mangled blind slat), I&amp;rsquo;ve perfected a system that opens my blinds based on either time schedules or ambient light conditions.</description></item><item><title>Automate Your Curtains with a Smart Tuya Roller Chain Motor: A Step-by-Step Guide</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/automate-curtains-tuya-smart-roller-chain-motor-guide/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/automate-curtains-tuya-smart-roller-chain-motor-guide/</guid><description>Automate Your Curtains with a Smart Tuya Curtain Roller Chain Motor Ever wished your curtains could open and close on their own? Maybe you’re tired of fumbling with cords in the morning or want to impress your friends with a &amp;ldquo;Hey Google, open the curtains&amp;rdquo; moment. Whatever your reason, automating your curtains with a Tuya Smart Curtain Roller Chain Motor is easier than you think. Here’s how I did it—and how you can too.</description></item><item><title>Track Your Electricity Consumption with Shelly Pro 2PM: Advantages and Home Assistant Integration</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/track-electricity-consumption-shelly-pro-2pm-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/track-electricity-consumption-shelly-pro-2pm-home-assistant/</guid><description>Track Your Electricity Consumption with Shelly Pro 2PM: Advantages and Home Assistant Integration Ever stared at your electricity bill and wondered, &amp;ldquo;How did I use that much power?&amp;quot; I certainly have. That’s why I decided to take control by monitoring my home’s energy consumption in real-time using the Shelly Pro 2PM—a versatile, Wi-Fi-enabled energy monitoring device. In this guide, I’ll walk you through setting it up, integrating it with Home Assistant, and turning raw data into actionable insights.</description></item><item><title>DIY Smart Door Sensor with ESP32 and Home Assistant: A Step-by-Step Guide</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/diy-smart-door-sensor-esp32-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/diy-smart-door-sensor-esp32-home-assistant/</guid><description>DIY Smart Door Sensor with ESP32 and Home Assistant Ever walked out the door and wondered, Did I close it? I’ve been there too—until I built a DIY smart door sensor using an ESP32 and Home Assistant. Now, my phone buzzes if the door’s left ajar, and I’ve even set up automations to turn off the AC when the door’s open for too long (goodbye, wasted energy!). Here’s how you can build your own.</description></item></channel></rss>