<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>DIY on</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/tags/diy/</link><description>Recent content in DIY on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omarghader.github.io/tags/diy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Build an AM312 Presence Detector Using ESP32 and Home Assistant</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-am312-presence-detector-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/esp32-am312-presence-detector-home-assistant/</guid><description>Build an AM312 Presence Detector Using ESP32 and Home Assistant Ever walked into a room and wished the lights would just know to turn on? That’s the magic of presence detection—no clapping, no waving, just pure automation. In this guide, I’ll show you how to build a DIY presence detector using an AM312 PIR sensor and ESP32, then integrate it with Home Assistant for seamless smart home control.
I’ve tinkered with a dozen motion sensors, but the AM312 is a standout for its low power consumption and compact size.</description></item><item><title>Track Your Electricity Consumption with Shelly Pro 2PM: Advantages and Home Assistant Integration</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/track-electricity-consumption-shelly-pro-2pm-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/track-electricity-consumption-shelly-pro-2pm-home-assistant/</guid><description>Track Your Electricity Consumption with Shelly Pro 2PM: Advantages and Home Assistant Integration Ever stared at your electricity bill and wondered, &amp;ldquo;How did I use that much power?&amp;quot; I certainly have. That’s why I decided to take control by monitoring my home’s energy consumption in real-time using the Shelly Pro 2PM—a versatile, Wi-Fi-enabled energy monitoring device. In this guide, I’ll walk you through setting it up, integrating it with Home Assistant, and turning raw data into actionable insights.</description></item><item><title>DIY Smart Door Sensor with ESP32 and Home Assistant: A Step-by-Step Guide</title><link>https://omarghader.github.io/diy-smart-door-sensor-esp32-home-assistant/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://omarghader.github.io/diy-smart-door-sensor-esp32-home-assistant/</guid><description>DIY Smart Door Sensor with ESP32 and Home Assistant Ever walked out the door and wondered, Did I close it? I’ve been there too—until I built a DIY smart door sensor using an ESP32 and Home Assistant. Now, my phone buzzes if the door’s left ajar, and I’ve even set up automations to turn off the AC when the door’s open for too long (goodbye, wasted energy!). Here’s how you can build your own.</description></item></channel></rss>